Finding Aid for J. Paul Getty Museum Exhibition Photographs, 1980-2004 (bulk 1990-2004) IA20032
Institutional Records and Archives
J. Paul Getty Museum exhibition photographs
1980-2004 (bulk 1990-2004)
1990-2004
Institutional Records and Archives
J. Paul Getty Museum
IA20032
14.8 Linear Feet (36 boxes)
The records comprise written documentation and photographs documenting the exhibitions of the J. Paul Getty Museum from the early 1980s to 2004. Materials include black-and-white and color photographic prints, slides, negatives, transparencies, and digital images (TIFFs).
Acquisition Information
Accession 2007.IA.36 was transferred by the J. Paul Getty Museum Imaging department in August 2007. Accession 2011.IA.43 was transferred by the J. Paul Getty Museum Department of Education.
Restrictions on Access
The records described in accession 2007.IA.36 and 2011.IA.43 are available for use by qualified researchers. Access is limited to in-person consultation in the Research Library Reading Room.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records document some of the exhibitions hosted by the J. Paul Getty Museum, both at the Getty Villa and Getty Center, from 1980 to 2004. The bulk of material issues from approximately 1990 to 2004 and is an incomplete record of Getty exhibitions, especially for those years prior to 1999. The records consist of photographs, slides, and other visual media. Nearly all of the represented exhibitions from 1980 to 2004 are documented by black-and-white 8 x 10 inch photographs and their associated negatives. Most exhibitions from the late 1990s through 2004 are also documented by color slides. Though the majority of files document temporary, special exhibitions of varying scope and significance, the installations of some permanent collection galleries are also included. The photographs were taken by Getty photographers working for the Museum Imaging Services department and its departmental predecessors. The photographs were taken at the request of various curatorial and conservation departments in order to document the exhibition installation process rather than the individual art objects.
Arrangement
These records are arranged in chronological order.
Administrative History
The J. Paul Getty Museum was established as a charitable trust in 1953 by oil tycoon J. Paul Getty in order to house his growing art collections. Getty had been collecting art since the 1930s. The J. Paul Getty Museum originally opened in 1954, with relatively little publicity, in two rooms of Mr. Getty's Ranch House in the Pacific Palisades near Malibu, California. By August 1955 the museum in the Ranch House had six gallery areas. In 1956 Mr. Getty began planning a new antiquities gallery, which was completed and opened to the public in mid-December 1957. Each year the number of museum visitors increased, and though Mr. Getty curtailed his art acquisitions activities beginning in 1958, the museum continued to grow.
In the fall of 1968, after considering various options for expanding the Ranch House, Getty decided to build a separate museum facility on the same property. This new museum was designed in the form of a first-century Roman country house, based primarily on the plans of the ancient Villa dei Papiri just outside of Herculaneum, Italy. The new museum facility opened to the public on January 16, 1974. Although Getty retained the title of Museum Director over the years, he never left his home in England to visit the new museum building, effectively making the Museum Curator or Deputy Director the on-site director. Getty monitored every expense and purchase made by the museum, and staff regularly traveled to Sutton Place, his home outside London, to consult with him on museum matters.
J. Paul Getty died in 1976 without ever seeing his new museum. Much to everyone's surprise Getty bequeathed almost his entire estate to the museum with a mission to promote "the diffusion of artistic and general knowledge." In 1981, when it became clear that the estate funds would soon be available, Harold M. Williams was hired as the first President of the museum trust. The trust then began a year of exploration to determine where it would focus its resources and energies in order to make the greatest possible contribution to the field of art and art history as a whole. The expansion of the Museum's collections combined with the new programs proposed by the trust would require a facility beyond what the Villa site could accommodate. In 1983 the estate funds became available, the trust's name was officially changed from the J. Paul Getty Museum Trust to the J. Paul Getty Trust, and the museum retained the name the J. Paul Getty Museum. The following year Richard Meier & Partners was chosen to design the Getty Center to house the trust, its newly created programs, and a second site for the Museum.
Today the J. Paul Getty Trust is an international cultural and philanthropic organization serving both general audiences and specialized professionals. The Trust is a not-for-profit institution, educational in purpose and character, that focuses on the visual arts in all of their dimensions. As of 2009 the Trust supports and oversees four programs: the Getty Foundation; the Getty Conservation Institute; and the Getty Research Institute; and J. Paul Getty Museum. The Museum serves a wide variety of audiences through its expanded range of exhibitions and programming in the visual arts from two locations in the Los Angeles area: the Getty Villa near Malibu and the Getty Center in Brentwood.
The J. Paul Getty Museum at the Center, which opened to the public in 1997, houses European paintings, drawings, sculpture, illuminated manuscripts, decorative arts, and European and American photographs. The J. Paul Getty Museum at the Getty Villa underwent extensive renovation and expansion from 1997-2006 and reopened to the public on January 28, 2006. The Villa houses works of art from the Museum's collection of Greek, Roman, and Etruscan antiquities. The J. Paul Getty Museum seeks to further knowledge of the visual arts by collecting, preserving, exhibiting and interpreting works of art of the highest quality. The Center and the Villa serve diverse audiences through the Museum's permanent collection, changing exhibitions, conservation, scholarship, research, and public programs.
Art -- Exhibitions; Photographic prints; Negatives (Photographs); Slides (photographs); Art museums -- Exhibitions; Getty Villa (Malibu, Calif.); Getty Center (Los Angeles, Calif.)
- Exhibition photographs, 1980-2004; (bulk 1990-2004); Series I.; 14.8 Linear Feet (36 boxes)
  Scope and Contents note
  The records consist of photographs and slides documenting the exhibitions of the J. Paul Getty Museum from the early 1980s to 2004. Media include black-and-white and color prints, slides, negatives and transparencies in addition to written documentation about the photography of included exhibitions.
  Arrangement
  These records are arranged in chronological order.
  - Exhibitions, 1980-1984
    - "Leonardo DaVinci: Nature Studies from the Royal Library at Windsor Castle,", 1980-1981; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - "Holbein and the Court of Henry VIII: Drawings from the Royal Library at Windsor Castle,", 1982-1983; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - Drawings gallery, c 1982-1983; (B/W prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - "Renaissance Painting in Manuscripts: Treasures from the British Library,", October 1983-January 1984; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm and 120mm color slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - Manuscripts exhibition, June 1984; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, color transparencies) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - Renaissance manuscript exhibition, undated; (Multiple folders; B/W 4x5 negatives, miscellaneous images) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
  - Exhibitions, 1986
    - Galleries 206 and 209, June 1986; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - Paintings conservation meeting, June 5, 1986; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - Manuscript gallery, September 1986; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
  - Exhibitions, 1988
    - Silver gallery, August 1988; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - "The Leiden 'Aratea': Ancient Constellation in a Medieval Manuscript,", November-December 1988; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
  - Exhibitions, 1989
    - "Experimental Photography: The Painter-Photographer,", July 1989; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - "Experimental Photography: The Machine Age,", October 1989; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
  - Exhibitions, 1990
    - Mount documentation, installation of Gallery 219, January 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - Porcelain showcases, installation of Gallery 219, January 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-1)
    - "Domestic Idylls: Photographs by Lady Hawarden from the Victoria and Albert Museum,", January 13, 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - "Experimental Photography: The New Subjectivity,", January 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - "Paul Strand: People and Place,", January 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - "Carleton Watkins: Western Landscape and the Classical Vision, ", April 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - Gallery 206, June 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Installation of Gallery 219, August 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - "Persistent Themes: Notable Photography Acqusitions, 1985-1990, ", June 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - Gallery 210, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 215, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 217, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 219, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 220, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 221, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 223, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 224, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 225, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Gallery 226, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Browsing room, September 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Villa galleries 107, 108, 115, 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Galleries 116, 117, 118, 119, 120 and 123, 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Galleries 202, 203, 204 and vestibule, October 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Galleries 205, 208, 228, 229, October 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-2)
    - Manuscripts gallery, October 1, 1990; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
  - Exhibitions, 1991
    - "L'arte del Vasaio: The Italian Renaissance Potters' Art,", February 1991; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints; 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "Neither Speech nor Language,", April 1991; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - "August Sander: Faces of the People,", June 1991; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - Anco Engineering Company, Testing of mock art objects for conservation, June 1991; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "Lisette Model: Daring to See,", August 1991; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-3)
    - "Atget's Magical Analysis: Photographs, 1915-1927,", December 1991; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
  - Exhibitions, 1992
    - "Innocent Bystander: The Restoration of Orazio Gentileschi's Madonna and Child, January 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "Grave Testimony: Photographs of the Civil War,", February 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "The Dubois Corner Cabinet: A Closer Look,", March 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "Walker Evans: An Alabama Record,", June 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "The Dubois Corner Cabinet" interactive exhibition objects, July 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "Two Lives: O'Keeffe by Stieglitz, 1917-1923,", August 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-4)
    - "Manuel Alvarez Bravo: Recuerdo de unos años,", November 1992; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "In the Tomb of Nefertari,", 1992-1993; (Multiple folders; B/W prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-18)
  - Exhibitions, 1993
    - "Silvy's River Scene, France: The Story of a Photograph,", January 1993; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "Fame and Photography,", May 1993; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "Drawings by Giovanni Battista Tiepolo from the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, ", June 1993; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - "Being and Becoming: Photographs by Edmund Teske,", August 1993; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "Women on the Edge: Twenty Photographers in Europe, 1919-1939,", October 1993; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "Gilding the Dome of Heaven: Gold Ground Paintings in Medieval and Renaissance Italy,", October 1993; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
  - Exhibitions, 1994
    - "Little Pictures,", January 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "Palette of Light: Hand crafted Photographs, 1898-1914,", May 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-6)
    - "Fouquet's Century: Transformations in French Painting, 1415-1530,", June 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "André Kertész: A Centennial Tribute,", August 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-5)
    - "The Heart of the Storm: Northern California Pictorialism,", September 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-6)
    - "Ars et Ingenium: The Illuminator's Craft and Genius,", September 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm and 120mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-6)
    - Rogier Van der Weyden's Madonna and Child, September 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "The Making of a Medieval Book,", November 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-6)
    - "Frederick Sommer: Poetry and Logic,", December 1994; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-6)
    - "A Passion for Antiquities: Ancient Art from the Collection of Barbara and Lawrence Fleischman,", 1994-1995; (Multiple folders; B/W prints, 35mm color slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
  - Exhibitions, 1995
    - "Michelangelo's Holy Family with Infant St. John the Baptist Seen in Context,", March 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - "Hidden Witness: African Americans in Early Photography" and "Carrie Mae Weems Reacts to Hidden Witness,", April 1995; (Multiple folders; 4x5 and 120mm B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, 3.5x5 color prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - J. Paul Getty Museum wood symposium, April 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "The Earl and Countess of Arundel: Renaissance Collectors,", August 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "The Earl and Countess of Arundel: Renaissance Collectors" interactive exhibition, August 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "Vision in Motion: The Photographs of László Moholy-Nagy,", October 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-8)
    - "Book Arts of Isfahan: Diversity and Identity in Seventeenth Century Persia,", December 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
    - "Alfred Stieglitz: Seen and Unseen,", December 1995; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
    - Joyce Plester's paintings conservation exhibition, undated; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints) (Box 2007.IA.36-7)
  - Exhibitions, 1996
    - "Albert Renger-Patzsch: The Magic of Material Things,", March 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
    - "The Crucifixion in Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts,", April 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - "Ten Centuries of French Illumination,", June 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - "Doris Ulmann: Photography and Folklore,", June 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
    - "Roger Fenton: The Orientalist Suite,", August 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
    - "Julia Margaret Cameron: The Creative Process,", November 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
    - "The Making of a Hero: Alexander the Great from Antiquity to the Renaissance,", December 1996; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
  - Exhibitions, 1997
    - "The Eye of Sam Wagstaff,", February 1997; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-9)
    - "Beyond Beauty: Antiquities as Evidence,", November 1997; (Multiple folders; color negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - Hall of Tapestries, 1997; (color 4x5 slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
  - Exhibitions, 1998
    - "Irresistible Decay: Ruins Reclaimed,", February 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - "Master Drawings from the J. Paul Getty Museum,", February 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - "Masterpieces of Medieval and Renaissance Manuscript Illumination,", March 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-12)
    - Alexis Smith, March 1998 (Box 2007.IA.36-11)
      - Restaurant plates, March 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-11)
      - "A Matter of Taste,", March 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm & 4x5 color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-11)
    - "Capturing Time: A Celebration of Photography,", April 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
    - Ed Ruscha, May-July 1998 (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
      - Pre-conservation photography of Ruscha drawings for exhibition, May 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm and 4x5 color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
      - "Ed Ruscha's Light,", July 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - "Out of Bounds: Marginal Imagery in Illuminated Manuscripts" and "Prayer Book for a Queen: The Hours of Jeanne d'Évreux,", June 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-12)
    - Decorative Arts gallery S113, June 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-14)
    - "The Art of a Daguerreotype,", March-July 1998 (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
      - Exhibition documentation, July 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
      - Object details, March 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 4x5 and 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
      - EX.1998.1.24, "Man Assembling Daguerreotype Lockets,", March 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 4x5 and 35mm color slides) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
    - Sculpture galleries, July 1998; (Multiple folders; 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
    - "Landscape Drawings, 1500-1900,", August 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-10)
    - "Walker Evans: New York,", September 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-11)
    - "Ten Centuries of Manuscript Illumination in Germany and Central Europe,", September 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-12)
    - "The Stammheim Missal,", September 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-12)
    - "Fuseli to Menzel: Drawings and watercolors in the age of Goethe,", October 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
    - "Making Architecture: The Getty Center from Concept through Construction,", December 1998; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-13)
  - Exhibitions, 1999
    - "A Practical Dreamer: The Photographs of Man Ray,", January 1999; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-12)
    - "Flemish Illumination of the Late Middle Ages,", January 1999; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-12)
    - "Two Centuries of Drawings from Bologna,", January 1999; (Multiple folders; B/W negatives & prints, 35mm color slides, documentation) (Box 2007.IA.36-11)
    - "The Making of a Medieval Book,", March 1999-November 2000 (Box 2007.IA.36-11)